<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Sumith</title>
 <link href="http://sumith1896.github.io//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://sumith1896.github.io//"/>
 <updated>2015-05-10T08:53:26+00:00</updated>
 <id>http://sumith1896.github.io/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Sumith</name>
   <email>sumith1896@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Google Summer Of Code with SymPy</title>
   <link href="http://sumith1896.github.io//Google-Summer-Of-Code-with-SymPy"/>
   <updated>2015-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://sumith1896.github.io//Google-Summer-Of-Code-with-SymPy</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gsoc/GSOC2015.png&quot; alt=&quot;GSoC 2015&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi there! The Google Summer of Code results are out and I have been selected. As mentioned in a previous post, my project of &lt;code&gt;Implementing polynomial module in CSymPy&lt;/code&gt; has been selected and I get to work with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sympy.org/&quot;&gt;SymPy&lt;/a&gt; under &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/psf/&quot;&gt;Python Software Foundation.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The excitement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really thank the community for accepting a freshman do a project. The community over at SymPy is so helpful and the working environment real fun that has motivated me to take up this project.&lt;br/&gt;
My mentors are &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/certik&quot;&gt;Ondřej Čertík&lt;/a&gt; himself and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sushant-hiray&quot;&gt;Sushant Hiray&lt;/a&gt;, who is a previous GSoC-cer at SymEngine(then CSymPy).&lt;br/&gt;
I&amp;#39;d also like to congratulate &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/shivamvats&quot;&gt;Shivam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/isuruf&quot;&gt;Isuru&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/abinashmeher999&quot;&gt;Abinash&lt;/a&gt; for getting projects under SymEngine and all others who have been selected under SymPy and Python Software Foundations in general.&lt;br/&gt;
I am excited for the summer to follow and the great learning experience ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;SymPy and SymEngine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/gsoc/sympy.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SymPy is a Python library for symbolic mathematics. It aims to become a full-featured &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_algebra_system&quot;&gt;Computer Algebra System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (CAS) while keeping the code as simple as possible in order to be comprehensible and easily extensible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sympy/symengine&quot;&gt;SymEngine&lt;/a&gt; is a fast symbolic manipulation library, written in C++.
Plans to be the fast swappable SymPy core and also a CAS on it&amp;#39;s own. We are currently writing Ruby and Julia wrappers for it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SymEngine currently lacks a polynomial module which is very essential in achieving SymEngine&amp;#39;s goal of being the fastest CAS ever. Having a polynomial module is a core concern and implementing a fast module also help in achieving a fast series module and other modules. Once implemented, SymEngine will be more capable as a fast optional SymPy core which we think is good to ship before 1.0 and at the same time SymEngine becomes a powerful CAS on it&amp;#39;s own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the proposal &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/GSoC-2015-Application-Sumith-:-Implementing-polynomial-module-in-CSymPy&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more detailed description of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to a great summer and times to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>